어지러운 전국 시대.
It is the turbulent Sengoku period.
카라쿠리인이 사는 지팡구국에서는 군웅할거하여 밤낮으로 접전이 계속되고
Warlords keep on fighting day and night over
Jipangu State, where Karakuri people live.
카라쿠리 무예가들도 승리와 영광을 꿈꾸며 맹렬히 싸우고 있었다.
Karakuri martial artists were sharpening their swords, dreaming of victory and honor.
그리고 지금, 카라쿠리 무예가 제일을 꿈꾸는 터무니없는 영웅이 탄생했다!
And now, a wild hero has arrived, seeking to be the number one Karakuri martial artist!
무사시 등장이오!
Musashi is here-dasu!
카라쿠리 검호전: 무사시 로드
Karakuri Kengouden
Musashi Road
(The Story of Karakuri Martial Artist: Road of Musashi)
사내는 언제나 세계 한가운데서
A man always dreams of the day
제일 강해질 날을
in the center of the world to become
아! 아! 꿈꿔라
AH! AH! the strongest
마음의 칼을 넓은 하늘로 번쩍 쳐들어
Raise the sword of your heart high to the wide sky
모험의 길의 막을 연다
Raise the curtain to the road of adventure
지팡구국을 떠도는 검호
A skilled swordsman roams on Jipangu State
그 이름은 카라쿠리인 무사시
His name is Musashi, a Karakuri man
격렬한 승부의 소리는
The sound of fierce duels
눈부신 인생
makes life dazzling
싸웠던 어제보다도 오늘 강해진다
Battles of yesterdays make you stronger today
무예! 이도류 무사시
Martial Arts! Dual Blade Musashi
내일은 빛난다
Tomorrow will be glorious
격렬한 승부의 소리는
The sound of fierce duels
눈부신 인생
makes life dazzling
싸우는 한껏 고요함과 함께
Fight the utmost with the stillness
무예! 이도류 무사시
Martial Arts! Dual Blade Musashi
미간이 반짝였다 무사시!!
His eyes shined! Musashi!
멀리서 와서 홋카이도를 무대로 총력을 다해 싸운 한조와 무사시, 센히메 일행.
Came from a place far away, Musashi and Senhime's group has fought against Hanzo with all their force.
기나긴 싸움 끝에 오니히메는 죽고, 지라이얀도 무사시의 팀워크에 넘어갔다.
After a long fight, Onihime died, and Jiraiyan has moved by Musashi's teamwork.
그리고 한조는 카라쿠리 요새와 함께.
And Hanzo has gone with Karakuri Stronghold.
악이라면 제일!
한조의 부활이오
The Most Evil!
Hanzo Revives
기분 좋다!
This feels good!
에도 성에서는 이에야스의 귀국 명령으로 돌아온 센히메를 위해 경사 잔치가 펼쳐지고 있었다.
In Edo Castle, a celebrating party was going on, for Senhime, who was called back by Ieyasu.
센히메 님, 슬슬 준비해 주세요. 이에야스 님이 몹시 기다리고 계십니다.
Senhime, please be prepared soon. Lord Ieyasu is waiting very much.
네! 지금 나갑니다!
Got it! I'll be there soon!
기다렸소!
We've waited for you-dasu!
기다렸지.
You sure did.
무사시, 침 삼켜라.
Musashi, your mouth.
몰라보겠구나, 센히메!
You look quite different, Senhime!
당연.
Of course.
아, 아야마로 님.
Oh, Mr. Ayamaro!
이에야스 님, 소개해 주시지요.
Mr. Ieyasu, please introduce her to me.
아, 이 기회에, 히메, 아부라코지 님에게 인사를!
Oh, Hime, you should greet Mr. Aburakoji!
센히메 님, 처음 뵙겠소!
Senhime, nice to meet you!
자, 일동 모였으니 오늘은 경사롭다, 경사로워!
As all of you are here, what a joyous day!
자, 쥬베, 먹어라!
Jube, you can eat now!
예. 그럼 먼저 조림부터.
Yessir. Then I'll start with boiled fish.
자, 자, 히메, 네가 좋아하는 것만 모아 두었으니 잘 먹어라!
Hime, as you wanted, I've had them prepare all the foods you like!
아부라코지 님도 사양말고!
Mr. Aburakoji, east as much as you want!
그럼 마음놓고 먹겠소!
Then putting aside ranks!
저 못생긴 남자는 누구이오?
Who is that ugly man-dasu?
어?
Huh?
미야코 팰리스의 유서 깊은 조정의 13번째 남아, 아부라코지 아야마로 님.
Aburakoji Ayamaro is the 13th boy of the historic imperial court of Miyako Palace.
이번엔 성주님이 에도토피아 구경을 위해 초대하신 듯 합니다.
It seems that the feudal lord has invited him for the sightseeing of Edotopia.
그러고 보니 어쩐지 기품이 있는지 없는지...
By thew way, he somehow looks like he's without any grace...
눈코 위치만 바뀌면 너하고 딱 똑같네, 무사시.
He is just like you, if you move around eyes and a nose.
(홋카이도 특산품)
(Specialty of Hokkaido)
공주님께서의 선물, 진미 털게입니다.
These are hairy crabs, from the present of the princess!
-오, 훌륭하구나!
-그렇지?!
-What an excellent product!
-Isn't that right?!
게는 저도 크게 좋아하오!
Crabs are my favorite food, too!
아, 그, 그건 잘 됐소! 많이 먹으시오.
Oh, good for you! Well, eat as much as you want!
아, 내 게!
Hey, my crab!
괜찮지 않나, 히메. 아야마로 님도 기뻐하고 있잖니.
Isn't it great, Hime? Mr. Ayamaro is happy about this, too!
봐봐, 히메가 좋아하는 나물 단고야!
Look, it's potherb roll that you like, Hime!
자, 자!
Here, here!
진미이오!
It truly is a delicacy!
이에야스 님의 급한 귀국 명령. 이건 혹시 맞선 상대?
Lord Ieyasu has called us back urgently. Could this be a marriage interview?
맞선?!
Marriage interview?!
쉬잇!
Shh!
끝이오, 끝났소, 먹었소, 잘 먹었소! 이걸로 난 자유이오!
It's over, it's over, and the meal was great! Now I'm free-dasu!
그건, 그건 수고했습니다.
That's truly much appreciated.
마음고생한 건 나다. 무사시가 날 귀찮게 해서 배가 아팠구만.
I am the one who've gone through a deep inner struggle. Musashi was torturing my heart.
게 못 먹은 거 주제에 아니꼬운 놈이오.
You are doing that because you couldn't eat crabs. How sickening-dasu.
뭐야?!
What?!
이제 됐다. 둘 다 푹 쉬어라.
Well, that's enough! You two should get a rest.
잘 부탁합니다, 제니가탄 님.
I'm entrusting them to you, Mr. Zenigatan.
예, 알겠습니다!
Alright! Understood.
자자, 오세요, 둘 다! 더러운 곳이지만 제 집에서 일단 쉬시라.
Now, follow me, you two! It's not a clean place, but still you can take a good rest there.
그렇소! 푹 쉬오!
That's right-dasu! We'll take a rest-dasu!
제니가탄 님. 저는 여기서.
Mr. Zenigatan, I will leave here.
어라? 제 집에 안 오쇼? 사양할 필요 없습니다만.
Huh? Aren't you coming to my home? There's no need to decline.
제안은 기쁘지만 여행에서 여럿 배운 것을 혼자 조용히 다시 생각해 보고 싶습니다.
I appreciate your suggestion, but I would like to think again about what I have learned during the trip alone in silence.
그렇구려. 역시 말하는 게 다르군!
I see. You really are different!
그럼 실례하겠습니다.
Then, excuse me.
그럼, 코지로!
See ya, Kojirō-!
어?! 내가?!
What?! Me?!
그래, 에도 성을 안내해 줘라.
Right. Guide him Edo Castle.
무슨! 왜 내가 저 아부라코지 씨 비위를 맞추어야 하는 거야, 할아버지?!
No way! Why do I have to please that Mr. Aburakoji, grandpa?!
저, 저 분은 네게도 중요한 분. 싫어하지 말고 수고해라, 어?
T- that person is important to you, too. Please do that, will you?
아, 센히메 씨, 여기에 오셨습니까!
Oh, Ms. Senhime, you were here!
그럼 안내해 주시지요!
Then please guide me!
세, 센히메 씨! 기다려 주시오, 조금만 더 느리게!
M- Ms. Senhime, wait for me! Please walk slower!
기다리-
Wait-
어, 어째서!
W- why?!
술래잡기는 끝이오!
Tag game is over!
진짜!
Really!
아부라코지 님!
Mr. Aburakoji!
너 따위하고 놀고 싶지 않아!
I don't want to play with you!
더...
More...
어이, 지금 돌아왔다!
Hey, we're back!
어서 와, 당신.
Welcome back, dear.
오랜만이네, 무사시 씨.
It's been a while, Mr. Musashi!
어라? 당신은...
Huh? You must be...
설마 아카네 씨? 왜 여기에 있소?
Are you Ms. Akane? W- why are you here-dasu?
음, 왜냐니. 내 마누라다.
Why, eh? She's my wife!
마누라?!
Wife?!
이? 아카네 씨가 두목 마누라?!
So, are you the boss' wife, Ms. Akane?!
그 때 덕분이야. 정말 무사시 씨에게 감사하고 있어.
Thanks to what you did back then. I still appreciate what you did.
그러니까, 그런 거야.
That's what happened, you know.
-요! 일본 제일! 카라쿠리야!
-(나왔다!)
(in a Kabuki show, one would shout name when one's favorite actor shows up - 掛け声, kakegoe)
-Yo! Best in Japan! Karakuriya!
(Usually, hailing the actors is a mean of applauding them; it doesn't cause a nuisance to audiences)
아름답군.
Beautiful.
훌륭해.
Excellent.
이거야!
(決まった, kimatta is an usual reaction to a peak acting in a Kabuki play, but not his physical action)
Definitive!
무식한 놈아! 안 보인다!
You idiot! You're blocking my sight!
물러나라, 바보 자식아!
Sit down, you dimwit!
뭐야, 이 머리꼭지는?
What is this upward ponytail?!
제비가 무예하네!
It must be a martial swallow!
맛있는 냄새이오.
Something smells tasty-dasu.
어라, 미안해. 그렇게나 배고팠어?
Oh, I'm sorry. Were you that hungry?
아, 아니, 그런 건...
Uh, no, not really...
어라?
Huh?
이제 곧이니까 착한 아이처럼 기다려.
It's almost done, so keep calm and wait like a good kid.
착한 아이... 이오...
Good kid... is it-dasu?
적당히 좀 해라. 나중에 나도 입 대는 거야.
Behave! I have to put my mouth on that later!
훌륭한 차였소이다.
It was a perfect tea.
아, 더러워.
Ugh, that's filthy!
이걸 어쩐담...
What should I do?
이렇게 된 바...
This leaves me no choice.
아! 바퀴벌레!
A cockroach!
어디, 어디에! 난 바퀴벌레가 정말 싫소이다!
Where, where?! I despise cockroaches!
뜨거, 뜨거!
Hot, hot!
자, 사양말고 잔뜩 먹으쇼, 무사시 씨.
Don't hold back and eat as much as you want, Mr. Musashi!
그래. 아, 이것도 맛있어.
Yeah. Try this too! It's good.
어, 그렇소...
Oh, is that so-dasu...
젊으니까 팍팍 먹어야지!
Since you're young, you gotta eat well!
여기! 이것도 먹어라!
Here! Eat some of these too!
고맙소!
Thank you-dasu!
(천신: 일본 민간신앙 신토 신, 뇌신하고 동일하게 취급)
(天神, tenjin: the sky deity in Japanese folk religion Shinto, considered the same with the thunder god)
저기, 여보. 밥 다 먹으면 셋이서 천신 제사제에 가자.
Dear, let's go for the memorial ceremony for the sky deity!
오, 그거 좋네!
Hey, that's a good idea!
제, 제사제이오?
T- the memorial ceremony?
그래, 무사시 씨가 훌륭한 무예가가 될 수 있도록 기도해야지.
Right. We must pray so that Musashi will become a splendid martial artist!
응, 그렇지! 좋은 생각이네, 아카네!
Yeah, that's right! You sure know what to do, Akane!
무사시 씨, 제사제 좋아?
Mr. Musashi, do you like ceremonies?
정말 좋소!
I love them-dasu!
그래! 그렇다면 빨리 먹어버려야지.
If you say so, I gotta finish this up as soon as possible!
그렇게 허둥대면 몸에 안 좋아, 여보.
It's not good for your body if you hurry like that.
안 좋소!
It's not good-dasu!
음, 아름다워. 내가 봐도 무서울 정도다.
Yes. It's beautiful. Too beautiful that it scares me.
방심하면 안 된다.
You must not let your guards down.
돈타쿠
Dontaku
알겠다.
Understood.
무슨! 한조는 살아 있었다!
What?! Hanzo was alive!
질풍노도의 후반을 기다려라!
Wait for the stormy latter half!
카라쿠리 검호전 무사시 로드
Karakuri Kengouden: Musashi Road
아가씨, 어때? 구운 단고도 맛있어!
What do you think about this, miss? Fried dangos are good, too!
이 주변 사람들은 다들 행사를 좋아하니까. 어떠냐, 단고라도 먹을텨?
All the people around here likes events and ceremonies. By the way, do you want to eat some dangos?
어라, 단팥죽 쪽이 더 좋아.
Hey, sweet red bean soup is better!
나, 이제 배부르오!
I'm already full now-dasu!
뭔 소리냐! 단고 2줄이나 3줄 입에 안 넣으려?
No way! Don't want want 2 or 3 lines of dangos in your mouth?
그래, 무사시 씨잖아. 저 가게 단팥죽 맛있어.
Yeah, it's you, Mr. Musashi! That sweet red bean soup tastes good!
둘 다 먹어보고 싶소.
I want to try both-dasu!
자, 그래, 그래! 일단 단고다! 따라와!
Well, yeah, then! Let's begin with dangos! Follow me!
저런, 당신이 먹고 싶은 거 아냐?
Hey, isn't it you who want that?
무, 무슨! 그건 마찬가지잖아?
H- hey! That's same for you!
들켰나.
You knew it!
아니, 저걸로!
No, I'd like that more!
어? 어이, 왜 그러냐?
Huh? Hey, what's wrong?
어디 배라도 아프니?
Does your stomach hurt?
정말이냐? 속이라도 안 좋거나 한 거 아냐?
You sure about that? Aren't you sick?
무사시 씨, 무리 안 해도 좋아. 속이 안 좋으면 말해.
Mr. Musashi, you don't have to overdo it. If you do feel sick, then tell us.
두목, 아카네 씨, 고맙소.
Boss, Ms. Akana, thank you-dasu!
갑자기 왜 그러냐, 무사시 씨!
That was so sudden, Mr. Musashi!
나, 태어났을 때부터 엄마 얼굴은 모르오.
I do not know how does my mother look ever since I was born-dasu.
쭉 혼자로 사이좋게 같이 있어 준 건 오츠루밖에 없었소.
I was alone all the time, and only Otsuru became a friend with me-dasu.
이렇게까지 받아서, 나...
I am so grateful for doing all this to me!
뭐야, 얘, 길 한복판에서?
What is this guy doing in the middle of street?
어라? 울고 있어, 형?
Huh? Are you crying, bro?
길이라도 잃어버린 촌놈 아니야?
Isn't this guy just a bumpkin who got lost?
우엥, 여긴 어디야, 하고 말야.
Like, weh, where am I?
틀림없어!
No doubt about it!
뭔 짓이야!
What was that for?!
그렇게 이상하냐, 엉?
Was it that weird, huh?
사람이 울고 있는 게 그렇게 이상하냐? 멍청하게 입만 살아가지곤.
Is someone crying that strange? You sure have a big mouth, you know.
니놈 목젖이 발기해서 피해를 주고 있잖냐!
Your erected uvula is giving trouble to people!
그거 못 숙이겠으면 내가 그 입을 꼬매 줄까?
If you can't handle your big mouth, should I fasten your lips?
제니가탄 나리! 잘 못 알아봐서...
Zenigatan sir! I didn't recognize you...
쓸데없는 소리 더 하면 용서 안 한다, 이 자식아!
I won't forgive you again if you ever say something like that again, you bastard!
죄송합니다! 미안해요!
I apologize! Sorry!
같이 가!
Wait for me!
미안허이. 부끄러운 모습 보여서.
I'm sorry for that.
무사시 씨, 괜찮으면 언제까지나 우리 집에 있어도 돼. 그렇지, 여보?
Mr. Musashi, if you could, you can stay in our home as long as you want. Right, dear?
물론, 그렇고말고! 내가 괜찮으면, 아빠라고 불러주던가 하고!
Of course, why not? If you'd like, you can call me dad, you know!
나는 엄마.
I'm mom, then.
두목...
Boss...
기쁘오!
I'm happy-dasu!
이걸로 OK. 할아버지, 용서해.
This will do. Forgive me, grandpa!
바이바이!
Bye-bye!
드디어 센히메를 죽였군!
Finally we got rid of Senhime!
센히메 님!
Senhime!
뭔 일이냐!
Who's there?!
수상한 놈이다! 모두 나와라!
Invaders! Everyone gather!
한조! 살아 있었냐!
Hanzo! Were you alive?!
나는 불사신이라 말했을 터.
I told you I am invincible.
성에서 나가게 두지 마라! 꼭 잡아라!
Do not let him leave the castle! Get him!
무사시! 무사시!
Musashi! Musashi!
누구여, 이 밤중에?
Who's there, in this deep night?
서, 성에서 도망쳐 나왔다고?!
Y- you escaped from the castle?!
너무 무턱댔소.
That's a mess-dasu!
틀렸어. 이미 늦었어. 같이 또 여행가자!
Whatever! It's too late now! Let's go on a trip again together!
-아, 아니, 그게, 히메...
-나, 결정했어. 성 생활 따위 지루하고 답답해!
-Uh, you know, Hime...
-I've made a decision. Castle life is boring and stifling!
게다가 그 인간하고 맞선?!
And marriage with that guy?!
생각하는 것만으로 기분 나빠.
Even thinking about him is gross.
그렇게 나쁜 놈으로는 안 보였소...
He didn't look like a bad guy-dasu...
그럼 니가 같이 살아!
Then you go marry him!
-두목! 큰일입니다! 세, 센히메 님이...
-없소!
-Boss! This is bad! S- Senhime is...
-not there!
계셔?!
You're here?
아, 코지로다!
Hey, Kojirō!
아, 센히메 님!
Oh, Senhime!
잠깐, 이건 걷기 힘드오.
Hey, it's hard to walk here-dasu!
센히메 님 경호는 나 혼자서 충분하다!
I am more than enough for the guard of Senhime!
할아버지!
Grandpa!
오, 히메!
Oh, Hime!
-무사해서 다행이야!
-아, 너야말로 이불이 텅 비어 있어서 걱정했다!
-It's good to know that you're safe!
-I was worried about you since your coverlet was empty!
미안해. 그래도 말야...
I'm sorry, but you know...
정말 잘 되었소! 나도 걱정에 걱정을! 모두 내 공주를 똑바로 지키쇼!
What a relief! I worried so much! Everyone, protect my princess properly!
누가 니 공주야?!
Who's your princess?!
어차피 그렇게 될 거잖소.
That will nonetheless eventually happen.
이미 알고 있는 주제에.
And you know that.
영주님! 센히메 님은 무사합니다!
Feudal lord! Senhime is safe.
그래! 한조는 찾았느냐?
Great. Did you find Hanzo yet?
그게 아직입니다. 그렇지만 반드시 찾아내겠습니다.
Not yet, but I will find him no matter what.
정말, 내 대신 천하를 쥐어잡겠다니, 단연코 용서할 수 없다!
Really, trying to take over the country instead of me is unforgivable!
예! 영주님의 생명, 이 쥬베가 제 몸을 걸고 지켜 드리겠습니다.
Yessir! I, Jube, will protect your life risking my own body!
한조가 살아 있었다니 놀랐소이만, 이 엄한 경호 앞에선 이번에야말로 끝이오.
It's surprising that Hanzo's still alive-dasu, but with this level of guard in place, he's really gonna be done for this time-dasu.
그 한조라는 자, 얕보는 건 금물이다.
You must not look down of Hanzo.
아무도 없소.
There's nobody here.
네이놈!
You bastard!
할아버지!
Grandpa!
무섭소!
I'm scared!
역시 쥬베.
That's Jube I know.
한조!
Hanzo!
이에야스! 그 목숨 가져가겠다!
Ieyasu, I will take your life!
한 채 더 가지!
Take one more!
저런!
Damn!
한조! 못 달아나오!
Hanzo! You aren't getting away-dasu!
쳇! 오늘은 여기까지 하지!
Tch! That's all for today!
잡아라! 놈은 바깥으로 달아났다!
Get him! He ran to outside!
이 놈! 못 도망간다!
You bastard! You aren't getting away!
결국 한조의 품에 있던 것. 수상한 계획임이 틀림없습니다.
Anyway, the one in Hanzo's breast width has a suspicious plan written on it.
사이카이 왕국의 시라누이 일족이라?
(Saikai-do: lit. West Sea Circuit.
These administrative districts were used before Muromachi Era.
Shiranui: Atmospheric ghost light told in Kyūshū)
Shiranui clan in the kingdom of Saikai?
정해졌네! 괜찮지, 할아버지?
Well then! Am I good to go, grandpa?
에, 그렇지만... 뭐가 어떻든 규슈는 멀다.
Uh, but... no matter what, Kyushu is far away.
안 된다고 하면 가출할 거야!
If you say no, then I'll leave home!
어? 가출?
What?! Leave home?!
곤란하네...
That's bad...
영주님. 센히메 님도 여행에 익숙해졌기도 하고, 코지로 님과 무사시 님을 경호로 붙인다면.
Feudal lord, Senhime has become familiar with long trips, and as long as Mr. Kojirō and Mr. Musashi as her guards...
어, 그렇구나. 아무리 말해도 안 듣는 센히메이니 어쩔 수 없나.
Well, that's right. Senhime never listen to me no matter what I say.
좋아!
Yes!
이렇게 다시 셋의 온갖 일 다 일어나는 모험이 시작되었다.
And that's how their journey full of incident has begun once again.
사이카이 왕국에는 어떤 근사한 사내가 있을까?
What kind of wonderful man would be in the kingdom of Saikai?
규슈에 여행가는 사랑의 사냥꾼 센히메의 마음은 들뜬다.
The hunter of love Senhime is growing restless in her trip to Kyushu.
허공의 주머니에 달이
Sometimes the moon jumps over
뛰어넘어가는 일도 있어
the pocket of empty sky
큰 소리로 웃으면
Laugh loudly and
내일에는 아침이 와
morning will come tomorrow
잃는 것 따위는 아무것도 아니야
Don't worry too much about losing
계속 해나가! 앞으로 가!
Keep going! Go for it!
맨손은 강해
A bare hand is strong
그런 거야! 가볍게 가자
That's how it is! Let's go lightly
인생 그런 거야! 기회가 어라,
That's how life is! Look, a chance
꼬리를 흔들며 쫒아와!
follows us wagging its tail!
그런 거야! 가볍게 가자
That's how it is! Let's go lightly
미래도 그런 거야! 내일이 어라,
That's how the future is, too! Look, tomorrow
양손을 벌리고 웃고 있어!
is opening its hands and smiling at us!
단고 빨리 먹기 콩쿠르에 출전했다는 이유만으로 코지로하고 싸우고, 센짱은 시라누이 일족에게 잡히고, 엉망진창!
Just because I entered dango quick eating contest I fought with Kojirō,
Sen-chan was taken by Shiranui clan, and it's a mess!
그 때, 사이고 씨하고 오랜만에 료마 씨하고 만났소!
At that moment, I met Mr. Saigo and Mr. Ryoma who I didn't see for a long time-dasu!
센짱, 기다리시오! 내가 구하러 가오!
Sen-chan, wait for me! I'm going to rescue you-dasu!
다음 이야기! 사이고 씨는 수수께끼의 인물이오
Next story! Mr. Saigo is a Mysterious Person
질풍노도의 "나는 듯이"이오!
(翔ぶが如く, Tobu ga Gotoku: lit. as if in flight. Historical fiction written by Shiba Ryōtaro, where one of main character is Saigō Takamori)
It's a stormy Tobu ga Gotoku-dasu!
다음 이야기
사이고 씨는
수수께끼의 인물
기대하세요!
Next Episode
Mr. Saigo is
a Mysterious Person
Look forwards for it!